

At the forefront of **Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), Artificial Intelligence (AI), and User Experience (UX),** my research focuses on designing and evaluating human-AI collaborative tools for improved usability and UX analysis. Honored with the 2023 **Google PhD Fellowship in HCI**, my work not only advances technology but also champions accessibility, focusing on inclusive computing education and assistive technology for diverse user groups.

Education

Rochester Institute of Technology

Rochester, NY, US

Aug 2020 - present

PhD in Computing and Information Sciences

- Advised by Dr. Kristen Shinohara and Dr. Mingming Fan
- Committee members: Dr. Cecilia O Alm, Dr. Garreth Tigwell, and Dr. Jian Zhao
- Participating in the AWARE-AI NSF Research Traineeship (NRT) Program

University of Waterloo

Waterloo, ON, CA

Sept 2015 - Apr 2020

BASC IN BIOMEDICAL ENGINEERING

- Capstone advised by Dr. John Zelek
- · Graduated on Dean's Honour List

Experience

Rochester Institute of Technology

Rochester, NY, US

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Aug 2020 - present

- Conduct research at the intersection of HCI and AI, focusing on the human-centered design of human-AI collaborative tools to enhance usability analysis
- Design, execute, and analyze diverse research studies using methods such as interviews, surveys, design probes, usability tests, and quantitative experiments
- Author technical papers for peer-reviewed publication and create strategic dissemination plans to share research insights with broader audiences

Autodesk, HCI & Visualization Research Group

Toronto, ON, CA

RESEARCH INTERN

May 2024 - Sept 2024

- Led a mixed-methods research project on integrating generative AI into 3D computer-aided design
- Authored a paper detailing novel findings (currently under review), influencing cross-team research initiatives
- Delivered high-impact presentations, including a direct presentation to the Autodesk CEO and VP of Research, effectively communicating research insights

Meta, Reality Labs

Seattle, WA, US

UX RESEARCH INTERN

May 2023 - Aug 2023

- Designed and led a 20-participant interview study about using VR headsets, efficiently collaborating with research vendors
- Played an active role in project brainstorming workshops and internal product demonstrations, driving innovative solutions
- Effectively communicated research findings to diverse product stakeholders, fostering a deep understanding of user needs and perspectives to guide product development

Meta, Reality Labs UX RESEARCH INTERN

Burlingame, CA, US

May 2022 - Aug 2022

- · Conducted in-depth literature reviews and authored reports to inform the design of Ray-Ban | Meta smartglasses
- Designed and conducted a user study with 30 participants to investigate audio performance
- Presented study results to over 100 stakeholders, including researchers, engineers, and cross-functional teams, leading to product design changes based on data-driven recommendations

LAST UPDATED: OCT 2024

Toronto, ON, CA

Research Intern May 2021 - Aug 2021

• Contributed to the DARPA Automating Scientific Knowledge Extraction (ASKE) program, driving advancements in Al-powered knowledge extraction systems

• Designed wireframes and implemented new features for the human-machine interface (HMI) of a visual analytics system, enabling multi-scale graph analysis and facilitating knowledge discovery

Huawei Technologies Canada, Human-Machine Interaction (HMI) Lab

Markham, ON, CA

RESEARCH ENGINEER

Jan - Aug 2019, May - Aug 2020

- Developed and trained machine learning models for gesture recognition utilizing TensorFlow, enhancing the accuracy and responsiveness of gesture-based interactions
- Conducted user experiments to explore innovative mid-air and edge-based interaction techniques, contributing insights presented at the Huawei Developer Conference 2019

University of Waterloo, Vision and Image Processing (VIP) Lab

Waterloo, ON, CA

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

May 2016 - Apr 2018

- Designed and 3D-printed a lens-free microscope and smartphone spectrometer, advancing portable optical technology
- Conducted tests to validate the precision and effectiveness of the devices

Publications

Note: In HCI, conference proceedings are the primary way to publish research. Conference papers undergo peer review, typically with 2-3 external reviewers and 2 associate chair reviewers. Acceptance rates for the main HCI conferences range between 20% and 25%, making them highly competitive. Authors with equal contributions are indicated with an asterisk (*).

CONFERENCE PAPERS (PEER-REVIEWED)

[C.14] Al as a Bridge Across Ages: Exploring The Opportunities of Artificial Intelligence in Supporting Inter-Generational Communication in Virtual Reality

QIUXIN DU*, XIAOYING WEI*, JIAWEI LI, **EMILY KUANG**, JIE HAO, DONGDONG WEN, MINGMING FAN Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction. CSCW. 2024 (In press)

[C.13] Bridging the Literacy Gap for Adults: Understanding How Streamers Teach Adult Literacy on Livestreaming Platforms

SHIHAN FU, JIANHAO CHEN, **EMILY KUANG**, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 DOI: 10.1145/3613904.3642423

[C.12] Designing Unobtrusive Modulated Electrotactile Feedback on Fingertip Edge to Assist Blind and Low Vision (BLV) People in Comprehending Charts

CHUTIAN JIANG*, YINAN FAN*, JUNAN XIE, EMILY KUANG, KAIHAO ZHANG, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024

DOI: 10.1145/3613904.3642546 Best Paper Honorable Mention (Top 5%)

[C.11] Exploring the Opportunity of Augmented Reality (AR) in Supporting Older Adults Explore and Learn Smartphone Applications

XIAOFU JIN, WAI TONG, XIAOYING WEI, XIAN WANG, **EMILY KUANG**, XIAOYU MO, HUAMIN QU, MINGMING FAN Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 DOI: 10.1145/3613904.3641901

[C.10] Mapping Accessibility Assignments into Core Computer Science Topics: An Empirical Study with Interviews and Surveys of Instructors and Students

EMILY KUANG, SELAH BELLSCHEIDT, DI PHAM, KRISTEN SHINOHARA, CATHERINE M. BAKER, YASMINE N. ELGLALY Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 DOI: 10.1145/3613904.3642097

[C.9] Enhancing UX Evaluation Through Collaboration with Conversational AI Assistants: Effects of Proactive Dialogue and Timing

LAST UPDATED: OCT 2024 2

EMILY KUANG, MINGHAO LI, MINGMING FAN, KRISTEN SHINOHARA

Proceedings of the 2024 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 26.3%], 2024 DOI: 10.1145/3613904.3642168

[C.8] Exploring the Impact of Artificial Intelligence-Generated Content (AIGC) Tools on Social Dynamics in UX Collaboration

ZIYAN WANG, LUYAO SHEN, EMILY KUANG, SHUMENG ZHANG, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2024 ACM Conference on Designing Interactive Systems [Acceptance rate: 27.4%], 2024 DOI: 10.1145/3643834.3660703

[C.7] Understanding Strategies and Challenges of Conducting Daily Data Analysis (DDA) Among Blind and Lowvision People

CHUTIAN JIANG, WENTAO LEI, **EMILY KUANG**, TENG HAN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 25th ACM SIGACCESS Conference on Computers and Accessibility [Acceptance rate: 30.2%], 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3597638.3608423

[C.6] Enhancing Older Adults' Gesture Typing Experience Using the T9 Keyboard on Small Touchscreen Devices EMILY KUANG, RUIHUAN CHEN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 27.6%], 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581105

[C.5] Collaboration with Conversational AI Assistants for UX Evaluation: Questions and How to Ask them (Voice vs. Text)

EMILY KUANG, EHSAN JAHANGIRZADEH SOURE, MINGMING FAN, JIAN ZHAO, KRISTEN SHINOHARA

Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 27.6%], 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581247

[C.4] Bridging the Generational Gap: Exploring How Virtual Reality Supports Remote Communication Between Grandparents and Grandchildren

XIAOYING WEI, YIZHENG GU, EMILY KUANG, XIAN WANG, BEIYAN CAO, XIAOFU JIN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 27.6%], 2023

DOI: 10.1145/3544548.3581405

[C.3] "Merging Results Is No Easy Task": An International Survey Study of Collaborative Data Analysis Practices Among UX Practitioners

EMILY KUANG, XIAOFU JIN, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems [Acceptance rate: 24.7%], 2022 DOI: 10.1145/3491102.3517647

[C.2] "Too old to bank digitally?": A Survey of Banking Practices and Challenges Among Older Adults in China XIAOFU JIN, EMILY KUANG, MINGMING FAN

Proceedings of the 2021 ACM Designing Interactive Systems Conference [Acceptance rate: 27.7%], 2021 DOI: 10.1145/3461778.3462127

[C.1] Compensated lens-free light field spectroscopy

Ameneh Boroomand, Mohammad Shafiee, Linda Wang, Emily Kuang, Farnoud Kazemzadeh, Alexander Wong International Conference on Inverse Problems in Engineering, 2017

JOURNAL ARTICLES (PEER-REVIEWED)

[J.3] CoUX: Collaborative Visual Analysis of Think-Aloud Usability Test Videos for Digital Interfaces

EHSAN JAHANGIRZADEH SOURE*, EMILY KUANG*, MINGMING FAN, JIAN ZHAO

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics. 281 pp. 643–653. 2022

DOI: 10.1109/TVCG.2021.3114822

[J.2] Compact, Field-Portable Lens-free Microscope using Superresolution Spatio-Spectral Light-field Fusion

FARNOUD KAZEMZADEH, **EMILY KUANG**, ALEXANDER WONG

Journal of Computational Vision and Imaging Systems. 21. 2016

DOI: 10.15353/vsnl.v2i1.105

$[\mathrm{J.1}]$ Enhanced Smartphone Spectroscopy via High-throughput Computational Slit

EMILY KUANG, FARNOUD KAZEMZADEH, ALEXANDER WONG

LAST UPDATED: OCT 2024

EXTENDED ABSTRACTS & WORKSHOP PAPERS (PEER-REVIEWED)

[P.2] Crafting Human-AI Collaborative Analysis for User Experience Evaluation

EMILY KUANG

In Extended Abstracts of the 2023 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, 2023 DOI: 10.1145/3544549.3577042 (Accepted to the Doctoral Consortium)

[P.1] A Multi-scale Visual Analytics Approach for Exploring Biomedical Knowledge

Fahd Husain, Rosa Romero-Gómez, **Emily Kuang**, Dario Segura, Adam Carolli, Lai Chung Liu, Manfred Cheung, Yohann Paris

Proceedings of the Workshop on Visual Analytics in Healthcare (VAHC), 2021

DOI: 10.1109/VAHC53616.2021.00010 Best Paper Award **?**

Honors and Awards _____

RECEIVED DURING PHD

- 2024 Best Paper Honorable Mention Award (Top 5%) [C.12], CHI
- 2024 Outstanding Graduate Student Award, RIT
- 2023 Google Ph.D. Fellowship in Human-Computer Interaction, Google
- 2022 AWARE-AI NRT Seed Funding Award, RIT
- 2022 **Department Nomination for Microsoft Research Ph.D. Fellowship**, RIT
- 2021 **Best Paper Award [P.1]**, Workshop on Visual Analytics in Healthcare (VAHC)
- 2020 Merit-based Ph.D. Scholarship, RIT

RECEIVED DURING UNDERGRADUATE

- 2018 **Experience Award**, Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada
- 2018 **President's Research Award**, University of Waterloo
- 2017 **President's Research Award**, University of Waterloo
- 2016 Undergraduate Student Research Award, NSERC
- 2015 **President's Scholarship of Distinction**, University of Waterloo

Invited Talks and Poster Presentations

Sept 2024	Poster presenter, AWARE-AI Inter-institutional NRT+ Summit	Rochester, NY
Jun 2024	Invited speaker, Womxn in STEM Conference	Toronto, ON
Apr 2024	Presenter, RIT Graduate Showcase	Rochester, NY
Jan 2024	Lead panelist , AWARE-AI NRT Retreat: Session on Resume Building & Internships	Remote
Nov 2023	Invited speaker, Youth Professional Career Development Series	Remote
Apr 2023	Poster presenter, CHI Doctoral Consortium	Hamburg, Germany
Oct 2022	Poster presenter, RIT Artificial Intelligence Summit	Rochester, NY
Apr 2022	Poster presenter, CRA-WP Grad Cohort for Women	New Orleans, LA

Teaching Experience _____

ISTE-798 Future Interactions

RIT

Jan 2024 - May 2024

- TEACHING ASSISTANT
- Collaborated with the course instructor to plan and organize course materials
- Mentored students and provided constructive feedback on assignments and research projects

LAST UPDATED: OCT 2024

GUEST LECTURES

Sept 2023	Human-AI Collaboration for UX Evaluation, PhD Research Colloquium (CISC896)	RIT
Apr 2023	Older Adults' Gesture Typing Experience, Design For Accessibility (ISTE266)	RIT
Nov 2021	Visual Analysis of Think-Aloud Usability Test Videos, Visual Analytics (ISTE782)	RIT

Service_____

SERVICE TO THE PROFESSION

I have reviewed 27 submissions to date, receiving 3 special recognitions for outstanding reviews.

Since 2021	Reviewer, CHI, CSCW, UIST, VIS, Chinese CHI, and Frontiers in Computer Science	
2023-2024	Associate Chair, Chinese CHI 2023-2024	
2024	Session Chair, CHI 2024	
2021-2022	Student Volunteer, VIS 2021 (virtual), CHI 2022 (in-person)	

SERVICE TO THE UNIVERSITY

2024	Panel Organizer and Co-Chair, AWARE-AI Inter-institutional NRT+ Summit
2023	PhD Student Representative, Board of Trustees Meeting
2023	PhD Student Representative, GRAD Open House
2023	Trainee Council Representative, AWARE-AI NSF Research Traineeship (2022-2023)
2022	Project Judge, Genius Olympiad

Additional Professional Experience _____

North Inc. (now acquired by Google)

COMPUTER VISION DEVELOPER

• Designed algorithm to quantify image sharpness for multi-camera system assembly

Synaptive Medical Inc.OPTICS ENGINEERING INTERN

• Investigated the stabilization of stereoscopic videos for a neurosurgical robot

St. Michael's Hospital

MEDICAL IMAGING RESEARCH ASSISTANT

• Worked on a video processing pipeline for non-invasive detection of diabetic foot ulcers

Kitchener, ON, CA

Apr 2018 - Aug 2018

Toronto, ON, CA Sept 2017- Dec 2017

Toronto, ON, CA

Jan 2017 - Apr 2017

Media Coverage _____

07/29/2024 Autodesk Research Intern Spotlight Video,	Autodesk Life
10/16/2023 Two RIT students earn Google Ph.D. Fellowships for AI computing research,	RIT News
10/13/2023 Google PhD Fellowship recipients,	Google Research
09/30/2023 AWARE-AI NSF Research Traineeship Program Newsletter (Trainee Spotlight),	AWARE-AI NRT

LAST UPDATED: OCT 2024 5